Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is פב, pe bet,
82. We pick up on the last line of פא עמוד ב
pe aleph amud bet and we're dealing with the whole idea of
קנאים פוגעים בו, kanayim pogim bo, of the zealots can act against
these people,
take the law into their own hands, vigilante justice, and we're going
to deal with the case that is the model of it, that
is the sort of the paradigm of this. Okay, והבא על הארמית,
v'haboh al ha'aramit, we're on the last line of פא עמוד ב,
pe aleph amud bet, 81B, and somebody who has intercourse with a
non-Jewish woman. בעי מיניה רב כהנא מרב, ba'ei minei Rav Kahana me'Rav,
Rav Kahana asked Rav, top of פב עמוד א, pe bet amud
aleph, לא פגעו בו קנאים מהו, lo pagu bo kanayim mahu, and
if the קנאים kanayim do not act, what's his status, how, what
type of a sin is this? You know, the whole sin of
intermarriage is based on the פסוק pasuk of לא תתחתן בם, lo
titchaten bam, you should not intermarry with them, but that's talking about
doing it in the context of אישות, ishus, of marriage, even though
marriage isn't binding, it's the context of אישות ishus in order to
transgress. But here, where it's just fornicating, casual sex, what exactly is
the sin? What exactly is the punishment that this person is deserving
of if it is not acted against by the קנאים? kanayim? So
מהו? mahu? So אינשי רב לגמריה, inshi Rav l'gmarei, Rav forgot his
teaching, he forgot what the פסוק pasuk that would teach what this
person's punishment is deserving of. אקריוהו לרב כהנא בחלמיה, akri'u l'Rav Kahana
b'chelmeih, so it was read to Rav Kahana in a dream, Rav
Kahana had a vision in a dream or something auditory and he
heard the פסוק pasuk being
read: בגדה יהודה ותועבה נעשתה בישראל ובירושלים כי חלל יהודה קודש השם
אשר אהב ובעל בת אל נכר. Bagdah Yehuda v'toevah naasta b'Yisrael u'biYerushalayim
ki chillel Yehuda kodesh Hashem asher ahav u'vaal bat el nechar. All
right, so אתא אמר ליה הכי אקריון, ata amar leh hachi akriyun,
so he came to Rav because he knew that Rav, you know,
couldn't answer this question about what the punishment is that this person
is deserving, he said I had this dream, this is the פסוק
pasuk that was read to me in my dream. So עד דכאבי
רב לגמריה, ad dkavi Rav l'gmarei, so that caused Rav to remember
his tradition, his teaching about this, and here's how he interprets this
פסוק: pasuk: בגדה יהודה זו עבודה זרה, Bagdah Yehuda zu avoda zarah,
Judah, you know, betrayed, this is עבודה זרה, avoda zarah, וכן הוא
אומר ובכן בגדתם בי בית ישראל נאם השם, v'chen hu omer u'v'chen
bagadetem bi beit Yisrael neum Hashem, okay, you have, you have betrayed
me, that's the whole essence of, you know, using the adultery metaphor
for our relationship with God and our fidelity to God, to betray
God is to worship עבודה זרה. avoda zarah. ותועבה נעשתה בישראל ובירושלים,
v'toevah naasta b'Yisrael u'biYerushalayim, an abomination was done, זה משכב זכור, zeh
mishkav zachor, that is the act of homosexuality, וכן הוא אומר, v'chen
hu omer, a man having intercourse with another man, ואת זכר לא
תשכב משכבי אשה תועבה היא, v'et zachar lo tishkav mishkevei isha toevah
hi, so focusing on the word תועבה toevah here, the abomination. Okay,
so that is that sin. So and so both of those are
sins that we know are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. כי חלל יהודה
קודש השם, ki chillel Yehuda kodesh Hashem, and Judah has desecrated the
holy one of God, the holy of God, זו זונה, zu zonah,
this is referring to sex with a prostitute, וכן הוא אומר לא
תהיה קדשה או לא תהיה קדשה מבנות ישראל, v'chen hu omer lo
tiheyeh kadesha o lo tiheyeh kadesha mibnot Yisrael, there should a male
or female prostitute is called a קדש kadesh or
קדשה, kadesha, excuse me, so לא תהיה קדשה מבנות ולא יהיה קדש
מבני ישראל, lo tiheyeh kadesha mibnot v'lo yiheyeh kadesh mibnei Yisrael, so
that is referring to that. Now that sin is not one that
is חייב מיתה, chayav misa, the sin of prostitution. Okay, ובעל בת
אל נכר, u'vaal bat el nechar, and has sex with a daughter
of a foreign God, זה הבא על הכותית, zeh haboh al hakutit,
someone who had sex with a non-Jewish woman. כתיב בתריה יכרת השם
לאיש אשר יעשנה ער ועונה מאהלי יעקב ומגיש מנחה להשם צבאות, ktiv
batreih yichret Hashem l'ish asher yaasennah er v'oneh me'ohalei Yaakov u'magish mincha
l'Hashem tzevaot, God shall cut off the person who does this, they
shall be,
you know, childless,
so מאהלי יעקב me'ohalei Yaakov from the tents of
Jacob ומגיש מנחה להשם צבאות. u'magish mincha l'Hashem tzevaot. So what does
this mean? אם תלמיד חכם הוא לא יהיה לו ער בחכמים, im
talmid chacham hu lo yiheyeh lo er b'chachamim, if he is a
Torah sage then he will have no place amongst the sages, ועונה
בתלמידים, v'oneh b'talmidim, a regular time amongst the students, he'll be cut
off from the בית מדרש. beit midrash. אם כהן הוא לא יהיה
לו בן מגיש מנחה להשם צבאות, im kohen hu lo yiheyeh lo
ben magish mincha l'Hashem tzevaot, and if you see a כהן, kohen,
then he will not be able to bring a offering on the
altar. Okay, so I mean that's interesting. It doesn't say he's חייב
מיתה, chayav misa, which is the case of the עבירות averos listed
at the beginning, and this punishment here is it saying that it's
כרת kares or is it just saying like he loses his social
status? You know, not exactly clear how the גמרא Gemara had it.
And then you have the case of the זונה, zonah, which is
in the middle.
You know, so it seems like no, everybody in the פסוק pasuk
gets the appropriate punishment for them. The beginning of the פסוק pasuk
was about חייב מיתה, chayav misa, then it talks about something that
is, you know, prostitution, which is a לאו, lav, and now it's
talking about this. punishment for somebody who acts this way that it
affects his status, but it doesn't really seem like it's different than
that. Although, again, the ראשונים, Rishonim, and we'll see this later in
the גמרא, Gemara, feel like how could there be a הלכה halakha
of קנאים פוגעים בו kana'im pogin bo that you're allowed to actually
take this person's life unless we assume that this person to some
degree is חייב מיתה chayav misa at least
בידי שמים, bidei shamayim, divinely deserving of death. So really coming down
and emphasizing the כרת kares השם Hashem part of the פסוק, Pasuk,
כרת kares which is not what actually the גמרא Gemara here is
emphasizing. Okay, let's keep on going.
So, אמר רבי חייא, amar Rabbi Chiya, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא:
amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba: כל הבא על כותית כאילו מתחתן בעבודת
כוכבים. kol ha-ba al kutis ke'ilu mis'chaten ba-avodas kochavim. If somebody has
sex with a non-Jewish woman, it is like you are making
the foreign gods, the idols, your מחותניסטות, machatenistas, like you are, okay,
so you're becoming family with these actual false gods. כאילו מתחתן בעבודת
כוכבים, ke'ilu mis'chaten ba-avodas kochavim, דכתיב: dich'siv: ובעל בת אל נכר. u-va'al
bas el nechar. He had sex with the daughter of a foreign
god. וכי בת יש לו לאל נכר? ve-chi bas yesh lo l'el
nechar? Does a foreign god have a daughter? אלא זה הבא על
כותית, ela zeh ha-ba al kutis, but it's talking about you have
sex with a non-Jewish woman that is connecting to all to the
foreign worship. Could be because like of the story of בנות מדין
b'nos Midian that it leads to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but it
could also be talking about why intermarriage has been seen, is seen
rightly as such a threat to Jewish continuity and our identity and
so on. You're bringing into the family this foreign god,
this whole thing which
is a violation of our sense of Jewish community and Jewish family.
Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. דכתיב. dich'siv. ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא, v'amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba, and רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said, we're
now just quoting because it's the same person, כתוב
על גולגלתו של יהויקים, kasuv al gulgolto shel Yehoyakim, it was written
on the skull of יהויקים, Yehoyakim, one of the later kings of
יהודה, Yehudah, the first
בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, who let the people continue to worship idols,
did not bring justice into the land,
was
given תוכחה, tochacha, reproof about that he needed to make things better
and bring justice and so on and he didn't listen to any
of that. And it says that if you don't do this, you
will die the death
of a donkey,
and your body will be cast out and so on. So he
said, and he didn't listen. So it says, so he says, it
was written on his skull: זאת ועוד אחרת. zos ve-od acheres. This
punishment that you got in terms of how you're treated in your
death and yet another one is awaiting you. So where do we
get that idea or what's that about? So the גמרא Gemara is
now going to tell us. זקינו דרבי פרידא, zakeino de-Rabbi Pereda, the
grandfather of רבי פרידא, Rabbi Pereda, which happens to be exactly the
person, the מנדאמר manda'amar we were just quoting, רבי חייא בר אבא,
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, I don't know why it doesn't say רבי
חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. Okay, anyway, so he אשכחה
לההיא גולגולתא, ashkecha le-hahu gulgolta, he found a skull דבשדיא בשערי ירושלים
de-vashadya be-sha'arei Yerushalayim that was cast off in the gates of ירושלים
Yerushalayim that was just rolling
around, דכתיב עליה: de-vikisiv alayih: זאת ועוד אחרת, zos ve-od acheres, this
and one other. He didn't, so he didn't initially know what it
was. This is the same רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya who said that
it was the skull of יהויקים, Yehoyakim, but initially he didn't know
what it was.
So קברה, kavra, he buried it, והדר נבג, ve-hadar n'vag, and then
it sort of
resurfaced, bubbled up to the top.
קברה, kavra, so he tried again to bury it, והדר נבג, ve-hadar
n'vag, and then again it sort of it pushed its way back
to the top, it resurfaced. אמר, amar, so then he realized this
was something special going on here. האי גולגולתא של יהויקים, hai gulgolta
shel Yehoyakim, this must be the skull of יהויקים, Yehoyakim, דכתיב ביה,
dich'siv bei, it says by him: קבורת חמור יקבר, kevuras chamor yikaver,
the burial of a donkey he'll be buried, סחוב והשלך מהלאה לשערי
ירושלים, sachov vehashlech mehaleh l'sha'arei Yerushalayim, dragged and cast outward from the
gates of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So it was found there in the gates
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So, and if it's a burial of a donkey,
meaning you won't be buried, so it has been divinely decreed that
his body cannot be buried. He still doesn't know what the זאת
ועוד אחרת zos ve-od acheres is going to be. But just wait.
Okay. אמר: amar:
מלכא הוא ולאו אורח ארעא לביזויי. malka hu ve-lav orech ara l'vizzuyei.
Okay fine, that was a divine punishment, he can't be buried, but
in the end he still was a king and he should not
be degraded in this way. So what did he do? It's not
proper for him to be degraded. שקליה, shakleh, he took the skull,
כרכיה בשיראי, karchah be-shiraya, he wrapped it in silk, ואותביה בסיפתא, ve-osvei
be-sifta, and he put it in a type of a box in
his room. אתתא דביתהו, asaya de-vis'hu, so his wife came, חזיתא, chazisa,
and saw the skull, as she was cleaning up, putting stuff away,
she saw, what's a skull in this box? נפקא אמרה לשיבבותה, nafkas
amrah le-shivevosah, she went and she told her neighbors, hey I found
this skull in my husband's box. So of course they suspected something
the worst or I don't know something improper. אמרי לה: amri lah:
האי דאיתתא קמייתא, hai de-it'sa kamaisa, that must be the skull of
his first wife, so presumably he did
He,
you know, he can't forget her, he's still in love with her,
and he has to even keep her skull around. That's what they
suspect. So שדייה לתנורא וקליה *Shadya letanura vekalya*, so he didn't want
any of that, so she threw it into the oven and she
burnt it into ashes. So that was the אות אחרת *Ot acheret*,
that was, it wasn't enough that he wasn't buried, there was yet
another punishment awaiting him.
Okay.
כי אתא *Ki ata*, when רב Rav. חייא בר אבא *Rav Hiyya
bar Abba* came, אמר היינו דכתיב ומואב אות אחרת *Amar hainu dichtet
uMoav ot acheret*, oh, now I understand what it means, what was
written on it, וזאת אות אחרת *ve-zot ot acheret*. Okay. That was
the end, that was a bit of a digression. Back to בועל
ארמית boel arammit? *Boel Aramit*. All right, so כי אתא רב Rav
דימי אמר *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar*, when רב דימי *Rav Dimi*
came from ארץ ישראל Yisrael? *Eretz Yisrael* he said, בית דינו של
חשמונאי גזרו *Beit dino shel Chashmonai gazru*, the בית דין *Beit Din*
in the time of the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim* made a גזירה *gezeira*, made
an edict. It's interesting why are they ascribing it specifically to the
חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*, but okay, that was the time of like
religious reformation and concern also about Hellenization and so on. And they
said, הבא על הכותית *Haba al hakutit*, somebody who has sex with
a non-Jewish woman—and again, it's not in the context of being married,
so it's not the biblical prohibition—so חייב עליה משום נשק"א *chayav alei
mishum nashka*, rabbinically we will treat it as four sins. נשק"א *Nashka*,
which stands for נדה *Niddah*, even though הלכות *halachot* of נדה *Niddah*
technically only apply to a Jewish woman, we're going to rabbinically treat
her as a נדה *Niddah*; שפחה *shifcha* as a slave woman, because,
you know, so
a woman that you're not allowed to have sex with is a
slave; גויה *goya*, okay, just for being non-Jewish, again even though in
the תורה *Torah* that's only about marriage, we're going to create at
least a rabbinic איסור *issur* of having sex with a non-Jewish woman
because of her status as a non-Jew. It's interesting that that's the
third that's mentioned, but it's easier to say נשק"א *nashka* than it
is to say גשנ"א *gashna* or something. And א' *alef* is אשת
איש *eshet ish*, presumably if she's married then even though הלכתית *halachit*
that marriage is not recognized except as it's relevant for בני נח
*Bnei Noach*, אשת איש *eshet ish* is one of the שבע מצוות
בני נח *sheva mitzvot Bnei Noach*, but it doesn't have the status
for Jews for what's considered adultery, but nevertheless we will treat her
as a married woman. So all of these statuses, even if they're
not דאורייתא *de-Oraita*, we're applying to her rabbinically. כי אתא רבין אמר
*Ki ata Ravin amar*, when רבין *Ravin* came he said, no, משום
נשג"ז *mishum nashgaz*. Not the status of the first three are the
same, but not the status of אשת איש *eshet ish*, but the
status of זונה *zona*, prostitute. נדה שפחה גויה זונה *Niddah shifcha goya
zona*. אבל משום אישות לית לה *Aval mishum ishut leit lah*, but
I don't recognize their marriage. Not only technically legally I don't recognize
it, you know, his view was, oh, you know, all these non-Jews,
they all sleep around. So we're not going to give her, you
know, even a rabbinic status of a married woman even if she
is married because marriage doesn't mean anything to them, but we will
give her a status of a prostitute.
So, אבל משום אישות לית לה *aval mishum ishut leit lah*. ואידך
*Ve'idach*, and the other one, רב דימי *Rav Dimi*, he holds נשייהו
ודאי לא מפקרי *nashayehu vadai lo mafkere*. No, the opposite, he holds
they do treat marriage seriously and, you know, maybe the non-Jews have
sex outside of marriage or before they're married, but, you know, the
men don't allow the women—also very interesting male control here—anyway, to, you
know, to sleep, their wives to sleep around. So they are faithful,
you know, in marriage and therefore I give her the status of
a married woman דווקא *davka* and not the status of a prostitute.
Okay, so that is just sort of telling us in terms of
what are the prohibitions associated with this thing which we say קנאין
פוגעין בו kanayim pog'in bo. *kana'in pog'in bo*, but what really are
the technical legal prohibitions? You know, this gets exactly to a case
of something, again, hard to understand why this is true by the
first two cases in the משנה mishnah? *Mishnah* about קוסם kosem, *kosem*
and קסוה *kesva* or whatever, המקריא *hamakria*, but anyway, but at least
this you understand I mean why we treat intermarriage so seriously at
a social level, much more than עבירות *aveirot* that technically are much
worse, right? This is a real, real threat. So, you know, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s trying to say what the formal הלכה halachah
*halacha* is, but the threat aspect is expressed by this idea of
קנאין פוגעין בו kanayim pog'in bo? *kana'in pog'in bo*. All right, now
we're going to get into exactly that point of קנאין פוגעין בו
kanayim pog'in bo. *kana'in pog'in bo*. איתמר
נמי itmar nami, *Itmar nami*, it was also taught: אמר רב חסדא
הבא לימלך אין מורין לו haba limaleich ein morin lo. *Amar Rav
Chisda: haba limalech ein morin lo*. Somebody who comes to ask, can
I go ahead and kill this person who's in the middle of
this act of sex with a non-Jew? We're going to see that
actually has to be during the moment that they are engaged in
intercourse. Okay, we do not tell him, yes, you can go ahead
and kill him, because the whole point about this is that it's
vigilantism and extra-legal, right? So it's—and you know, there's like this uncomfortable
relationship to the concept of קנאין פוגעין בו kanayim pog'in bo, *kana'in
pog'in bo* that to some degree we're sort of glad that it's
done, which is why there's this הלכה halachah *halacha*, but at the
other hand, like we can't, you know, condone acting outside of a
legal system and it's dangerous to have a lot of zealots running
around and taking the law into their own hands. So it's something
that, like, it may be can be accepted or even praised after
the fact, but we are not going to actually condone it. So
therefore, if somebody comes to ask, we do not tell him, "Yes,
that is the הלכה." halachah אין מורין לו. Ein morin lo. ולא
עוד, Velo od, and not only that, but just to show you
how much this is operating outside of the legal system,
I'm sorry, איתמר נמי, it was also taught, I skipped the end,
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabba bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, הבא לימלך אין מורין לו. If somebody comes
to ask, we do not rule this way for him. ולא עוד,
Velo od, and not only that, but if you really want to
understand how much this is operating outside the legal
system, אלא שאם פירש זמרי והרגו פנחס נהרג עליו. ela she-im pirash
Zimri ve-harago Pinchas neherag alav. That if זמרי Zimri separated from כזבי,
Kozbi, the woman he was having sex with, and פנחס Pinchas had
killed him when they weren't at the moment of having intercourse, פנחס
Pinchas would have committed murder. Okay, so number one, it's telling you
that the only right or, you know, I don't want to say
permission, but anyway, the only space for this קנאים פוגעים בו kana'im
pog'im bo is during that moment of intercourse. So very much limiting
it, you know, and when do you even have the opportunity to
have exactly that happening in front of you? But also saying that
it's not like, "Oh, but if he missed that exact moment, we'll
go easy on him." Like no, this actually would be an act
of murder what פנחס Pinchas is doing if it was not exactly
in those right parameters, and פנחס Pinchas could be executed for it.
נהרג עליו. Neherag alav. Not only that,
נהפך זמרי והרגו לפנחס אין נהרג עליו. nehepach Zimri ve-harago le-Pinchas ein
neherag alav. If זמרי Zimri had turned around and killed פנחס, Pinchas,
you know, when פנחס Pinchas was coming after him, זמרי Zimri would
not be punished, would not be executed. Why? שהרי רודף הוא. She-harei
rodeph hu. Because פנחס Pinchas is a רודף, rodeph, פנחס Pinchas is
running after him to take his life. And it sounds a little
bit like from this that what it is saying is that even
if he was still in the middle of this act of intercourse,
so even at that very moment that פנחס, Pinchas, you know, can
kill him and it will be said like, "Okay, קנאים פוגעים בו,"
kana'im pog'im bo, you know, that's something that again, after the fact
we're good with, but if also at that same moment that he's
operating in קנאים פוגעים בו, kana'im pog'im bo, he's also a רודף
rodeph against, you know, from a legal perspective, he's a רודף. rodeph.
And if זמרי Zimri were to kill him, זמרי Zimri would be
exonerated. So this is really the גמרא Gemara sort of trying to
hold both of these ideas about the קנאים kana'im and the legal
system at the same time. Okay. ויאמר משה אל שופטי ישראל. Vayomer
Moshe el shophtei Yisrael. משה Moshe said to the judges of Israel,
"הרגו איש אנשיו הנצמדים לבעל פעור." hargu ish anashav ha-nitzmadim le-ba'al pe'or.
Kill each one, you know, the people that are fornicating with בעל
פעור, Baal Peor, with פעור. Peor. הלך שבטו של שמעון אצל זמרי
בן סלוא. Halach shivto shel Shimon etzel Zimri ben Salu. So presumably
they were doing that and they started judging people and they started
executing people. So the tribe of שמעון Shimon went to זמרי. Zimri.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, "הן דנין דיני נפשות
ואתה יושב ושותק?" hen danin dinei nephashot ve-atah yoshev ve-shotek? They're sort
of executing people, presumably from our tribe, presumably שמעון Shimon was really
into this, and you're doing nothing about it? So מה עשה, mah
asah, what did זמרי Zimri do? עמד וקיבץ עשרים וארבעה אלף מישראל.
amad ve-kibetz esrim ve-arba'ah elef mi-Yisrael. He gathered twenty-four thousand of the
Jews because we know twenty-four thousand die in the plague that occurred,
you know, as a result of this. So we're assuming those are
the twenty-four thousand that were all perpetrators. He gathered twenty-four thousand and
והלך אצל כזבי, ve-halach etzel Kozbi, and he went to כזבי, Kozbi,
this, you know, the woman of this prince of מדין. Midyan. אמר
לה, Amar lah, "השמיעי לי." hashmi'i li. Listen to me, have sex
with me. אמרה לו, Amrah lo, she said to him, "בת מלך
אני." bat melech ani. I am the daughter of a king. Right,
כזבי בת צור, Kozbi bat Tzur, he was one of the מלכי
מדין. malchei Midyan. וכן צוני אבא. Ve-chen tzivani abba. My father commanded
me, "לא תשמעי אלא לגדול שבהם." lo tishme'i ela le-gadol she-ba-hem. Do
not agree to have sex except with the greatest one among them,
with משה. Moshe. So אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her,
"אף הוא נשיא שבט הוא." aph hu nasi shevet hu. Even he,
meaning I, am also the head of a tribe. You know, משה
Moshe is the head, I'm the head. ולא עוד אלא שהוא גדול
ממנו. Velo od ela she-hu gadol mimenu. He, meaning I, am greater
than משה. Moshe. שהוא שני לבטן. She-hu sheni la-beten. He is the
head of לוי, Levi, I'm sorry, I am the head of שמעון,
Shimon, which is the second tribe, והוא, ve-hu, and משה, Moshe, שלישי
לבטן, shelishi la-beten, is head of לוי Levi that is the third
tribe, so I am even greater, so yes you should have sex
with me. תפסה בבלוריתה. Taphsah be-vloritah. He grabbed her with her like
her ponytail, like, you know, her hair. Doesn't sound like he necessarily
was so ready to totally agree. But anyway, והביאה אצל משה, ve-hevi'ah
etzel Moshe, and brought her to משה. Moshe. אמר לו, Amar lo,
and he said to him, "בן עמרם," ben Amram, son of עמרם,
Amram, right, speaking in an obviously very belittling way to משה. Moshe.
"זו אסורה או מותרת?" Zu asurah o muteret? This woman, permitted or
forbidden for me? "ואם תאמר אסורה," Ve-im tomar asurah, if you're going
to say forbidden, because I know that's what you're going to say,
"בת יתרו מי התירה לך?" bat Yitro mi hitirah lach? Whoever permitted
to you the daughter of יתרו? Yitro? So he got משה. Moshe.
So go try to say to me that this is forbidden. You
know, רש"י Rashi comes immediately to the defense of משה Moshe and
says of course יתרו's Yitro daughter at הר סיני Har Sinai she
was part of, she was part of the people that stood at
הר סיני, Har Sinai, which is not exactly clear there in the
narrative, so she also became Jewish. But this is what he said
to משה. Moshe.
Okay, באותה שעה, Ba-otah sha'ah, נתעלמה ממנו הלכה. nitalmah mimenu halacha. So
probably because he was being personally attacked, he... The הלכה halachah escaped
him. The הלכה halakha seems to be not the הלכה of why
he could marry בת יתרו bat Yitro daughter of יתרו Yitro daughter
but about what to do with somebody in this circumstance.
So and the principle of קנאין פוגעין בו. kana'in pogin bo It's
actually interesting, why do you need the principle of קנאין kanayim פוגעין
בו? You know, there God said judge the people הנצמדים לבעל פעור.
hanitzmadim le'ba'al pe'or. So you know, that's what's so funny about the
whole thing that פנחס Pinhas is, you know, חז"ל Hazal are very
troubled with פנחס Pinhas as the model of a קנאי kana'i and
trying to limit it and sort of the passage we just saw
beforehand. And at the same time, what makes it extra-legal? Moshe was
said to take people and judge and judge the people that were,
you know, that were transgressing. Maybe what פנחס Pinhas did was somehow
in that context. All right, but maybe that would have to, you
know, be a whole trial and witnesses and so on. So anyway,
Moshe did not know and that's why פנחס Pinhas is seen as
sort of operating outside of that. So Moshe did not realize how
to handle this case, נתעלמה ממנו הלכה. nit'almah mimenu halachah. געו כולם
בבכיה, ga'u kulam bivchiyah, they all started crying. That's what the פסוק
pasuk says: והמה בוכים פתח אהל מועד. vehemah bochim petach ohel mo'ed.
והיינו דכתיב, vehainu dicheitiv, as what the פסוק pasuk says, והמה בוכים
פתח אהל מועד. vehemah bochim petach ohel mo'ed. Okay, so וכתיב וירא
פנחס בן אלעזר vecheitiv vayar Pinhas ben Elazar and פנחס Pinhas stood
up and he acted. So מה ראה, mah ra'ah, what did he
see? אמר רב, ראה מעשה ונזכר הלכה. Amar Rav, ra'ah ma'aseh venizkar
halachah. He saw what was happening and he remembered the הלכה of
קנאין פוגעין בו. אמר לו: אחי אבי אבא. Amar lo: achi avi
abba. He said to Moshe: brother of my grandfather, right? Because he
was פנחס בן אלעזר בן אהרן, Pinhas ben Elazar ben Aharon, so
brother of my grandfather.
לא כך לימדתני—it's Lo kach limadtani interesting, he didn't say משה רבינו,
Moshe Rabbeinu, anyway, you know, especially after Zimri said בן עמרם, ben
Amram, but okay, anyway it's a little interesting here about that does
not seem to be giving the greatest status to Moshe. Anyway, לא
כך לימדתני, lo kach limadtani, isn't this what you taught me בירידתך
מהר סיני biridtecha me'Har Sinai when you came down from הר סיני?
Har Sinai? הבא על הכותית קנאין פוגעין בו, Haba al hakutit kanayim
pog'in bo, that if somebody is having sex with a
כותית, kutit, the קנאין can attack him. אמר לו, Amar lo, so
Moshe said: קריינא דאיגרתא איהו ליהוי פרוונקא. karyana de'igarta ihu lehevei parvenka.
The reader of the letter, the reader of the, you know, like
the the message from the king, he should be the executioner. So
which is again, remember the גמרא Gemara said by that you cannot
פסקן, pasken, you cannot teach that the person, if somebody asks you
don't give them permission. So Moshe didn't say "Yes, you're right, go
do it." He suggested though, you know, you said it, so the
one who says it should be the one who acts on it.
ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, and Shmuel said:
ראש אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה נגד ה'. Rosh ein chochmah
ve'ein tevunah ve'ein etzah neged Hashem. He saw, you know, the the
פסוק pasuk which hadn't been written yet, but anyway he understood that
the principle that when it's God's honor is at stake, you sometimes
have to just not show deference to the bigger תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim and to the religious authorities who aren't acting, you have to
stand up and act. כל מקום שיש חילול השם אין חולקין כבוד
לרב. Kol makom she'yesh chillul Hashem ein cholkin kavod larav. When God's
name is being desecrated, you don't defer, you get up and you
act. רבי יצחק אמר רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yitzchak amar Rabbi Elazar, no,
what did he see? Something else. ראה, Ra'ah, what did he see?
שבא מלאך והשחית בעם. Sheba malach vehishchit ba'am. That the angel was
coming and destroying in the people and this מגפה mageifah was bursting
was was coming and he realized that he had to go ahead
and do something to stop it. So that's actually quite interesting, three
different takes. Right? Did he like sort of say like "Oh, this
is my obligation, קנאין פוגעין בו," you know, that's version one. Version
two is he just knew he had to act because nobody was
acting and he had to defend God's honor, which maybe is more
the simple sense of the פסוקים. pesukim. Like he got up and
he acted because he knew something had to be done, not, you
know, not like he had a tradition and he was checking his
tradition. And the third is, you know, he knew something had to
be done because people were dying and you had to act.
Okay.
ויקם מתוך העדה ויקח רמח בידו. Vayakom mitoch ha'edah vayikach romach beyado.
He rose up from the from the congregation and he took his
spear in his hand. מכאן שאין נכנסים בכלי זיין לבית המדרש. Mikan
she'ein nichnasim bichli zayin leveit hamidrash. So and some take the עדה
edah to be sort of like the בי מדרשא. bei midrasha. So
if he had to go get his spear, he first he went
מתוך העדה mitoch ha'edah and then he took his spear, so you
can't bring, don't bring your weapons into the into the בית מדרש.
beit midrash. We have that principle over there. Okay, so leave your
weapons at the door. שלף שיננה, Shalaf shinana, he took the blade
of the spear, הניחה באונקלו, hinichah be'unkalo, and he put it in
his tunic. Okay, because he, you know, he had to get to
the perpetrators, so he couldn't be obvious that he was going there
and trying to kill them, you know, he had to make it
a concealed weapon. Okay, so the blade he took off and he
put in his in his tunic. והיה נשען, Ve'hayah nishan, top of
פ"ב ע"ב, Pe-Bet Amud Bet, and he was leaning בהולך על מקלו,
be'holech al maklo, and he was using the the wood of the
spear, you know, to like a stick, like a like a cane,
and he was, you know, walking on it and using it as
a walking cane. וכיון שהגיע אצל שבטו של שמעון, Ve'keivan shehigia eitzel
shivto shel Shimon, when he came to the tribe of שמעון, Shimon,
אמר היכן מצינו ששבטו של לוי גדול משל שמעון? amar heichan matzinu
sheshivto shel Levi gadol mishel Shimon? He said, "Where do we ever
find that the tribe of לוי Levi is greater than that of
שמעון?" Shimon? He was leaning והולך על מקלו ve'holech al maklo and
he was using the wood of the spear, you know, the to
like a stick, like a cane, and he was walking on it
and using it as a walking cane. וכיוון שהגיע אצל שבטו של
שמעון, ucheivan shehigia etzel shivto shel shimon, when he came to the
tribe of Shimon, אמר היכן מצינו שבטו של לוי קודם משל שמעון?
amar heichan matzinu shivto shel levi kodem mishel shimon? He said, where
did we ever find that Levi, you know, is so holier than
Shimon? Like basically sort of saying like, oh, why are you leaving
me out of all of the fun? I also want to be
engaged in this type of a fornication. What, we're so we Levi
have to be so holy? So אמרו amru so the tribe of
Shimon says הניחו לו, hanichu lo, let him in. אף הוא לעשות
צרכיו נכנס, af hu la'asot tzorcho nichnas, he's also wants to take
care of his needs. He also wants to go ahead and be
part of this. הביטו פרושים את הדבר, habitu perushim et hadavar, look
even the פרושים, perushim, even the holy ones, even the people that
are generally very,
you know, צדיקים, tzaddikim, you know, even those are now saying that
it's okay. So that's what the people were saying and they let
him in. אמר ר' יוחנן, amar rabbi yochanan, ששה נסים נעשו לו
לפנחס. shisha nissim na'asu lo le'pinchas.
Six miracles were done for Pinchas when he was acted this way.
אחד echad number one, שהיה לו לזמרי לפרוש ולא פירש, she'haya lo
le'zimri lifrosh velo peirash, if Zimri would have separated, Pinchas would not
have had a right to kill her, kill him. ואחד ve'echad number
two, שהיה לו לדבר ולא דיבר, she'haya lo ledaber velo diber, Zimri
should have spoken up, he should have called all his, his whole
tribe was there. How did Pinchas manage to get through when he
saw what Pinchas was about to do?
Obviously Pinchas took the blade out of the tunic and attached it
to the spear. And then did what he did. Okay. ואחד ve'echad
another one, שכוון בזכרותו של איש ובנקבותה של אשה, shekivein be'zachruto shel
ish uvinvevatah shel isha, that when he speared them, he got it
right through their genitalia as they were engaged in this act of
intercourse, right?
And sort of alluded to maybe in the פסוקים pesukim how the
פסוקים pesukim could be read, but anyway,
but the חז"ל chazal understand that that was done so everybody could
sort of see how he justly acted, especially if that's exactly the
context of קנאים פוגעים בו. kana'im pog'im bo. ואחד שלא נשמטו מן
הרומח, ve'echad shelo nishmetu min haromach, and then that they did not
slip off of the spear because then he like walked out of
the tent, you know, where they were, you know, with them on
his spear and sort of held it up, this is how, again,
not in the פסוקים pesukim but what's being understood, so everybody could
see what's happened to them and how he acted justly.
So the, so a miracle is that they didn't slip off of
the spear. ואחד שבא מלאך והגביה את המשקוף, ve'echad sheba malach vehigbiya
et hamashkof, and the angel came and lifted up the lintel, the
lintel or whatever of the doorway of the tent so because if
he had
a stoop down to get through the doorway, they would have fallen
off the spear. Okay, so but to give him so that there
was good enough clearance. Okay. ואחד שבא מלאך והשחית בעם, ve'echad sheba
malach vehishchit ba'am, and then the final one is that the angel
came and they started bringing
this plague to the people and that got everybody very distracted so
they were not able to attack him after the fact.
All right. בא וחבטן לפני המקום, ba vechavtan lifnei hamakom, back to
the event.
Now that was, so he stopped the, so maybe the plague hadn't
stopped yet, maybe was still going on, and now he took the
two of them and he cast them down before God. Before God.
לפני המקום. lifnei hamakom. אמר לפניו, amar lefanav, he said before Him,
ריבונו של עולם, ribono shel olam, Master of the Universe, על אלו
יפלו עשרים וארבעה אלף מישראל? al elu yiplu esrim ve'arba'ah elef mi'yisrael?
For these 24,000 should fall? So he was maybe, so it sounds
like the 24,000 had already died and he's challenging God was that
a just act and we'll see maybe at least to get it
to stop at that moment and not go further. שנאמר ויהיו המתים
במגפה עשרים וארבעה אלף. shene'emar vayihyu hametim bamageifah esrim ve'arba'ah elef. Okay,
there were 24,000. והיינו דכתיב, ve'hainu dechtiv, that's what meant by the
פסוק pasuk ויעמוד פנחס ויפלל. vaya'amod pinchas vayefalel. Pinchas stood up and
ויפלל, vayefalel, which could mean he judged, but we're also very close
to the word תפילה, tefillah, he prayed. ואמר ר' אלעזר ויצפלל לא
נאמר, ve'amar rabbi elazar vayitpallel lo ne'emar, no it does not say
he prayed.
אלא ויפלל, ela vayefalel, and he argued or he judged. מלמד כביכול
שעשה פלילות עם קונו. melamed kivyachol she'asah pelilot im kono. He argued
with God. He said God, how are you doing this? How is
it just?
Maybe not all 24,000 had died but it was clear that they
were beginning to die and he wanted God to stop in the
middle. So ביקשו מלאכי השרת לדחפו. bikshu malachei hasharet ledachfo. The heavenly
angels wanted to push Pinchas away. Again, it's not exactly clear where's
Pinchas, he's up in heaven, I don't know, he's in the אוהל
מועד. ohel moed. Anyway, but they wanted to but say you have
no right, you're a human being, you have no right to speak
to God like that. אמר להן, amar lahen, God said to the
angels, הניחו לו, hanichu lo, leave him. קנאי בן קנאי. kanai ben
kanai. He's a zealot, a son of a the descendant of a
zealot. Rashi says this is referring to, you know, to Shimon and
Levi by Dinah which was also an act of, you know, sex
although a very different type of a case, rape, whatever. could also
be say maybe the לויים levi'im who got up at Har Sinai.
Anyway, you know, he's a descendant of a קנאי, kanai, it's he
comes by this, you know, honestly and he's very much לשם שמים.
leshem shamayim. משיב חימה בן משיב חימה. meshiv cheimah ben meshiv cheimah.
He's one to turn away God's wrath, the son of one who
turned away God's wrath. Aaron turned away God's wrath when there was
a plague by bringing the קטורת ketoret and that stopped the plague.
And now he's doing this and this is going to stop the
plague. So, you know, yes, he's he's coming by it very honestly,
he's very sincere in what he is doing.
Okay.
התחילו שבטים מבזים. hitchilu shevatim mevazim. The other tribes are not happy
with the way he acted. Like, you know, he comes out and
he kills one of them. But it's interesting, it's like all the
tribes. Okay, ראיתם בן פוטי זה, Ra'ishem ben Puti zeh, have you
seen this son of פוטי Puti שפיטם, shepitam, right, because why is
it called בן פוטי? Ben Puti? Because he's the son of אלעזר
Elazar and it says אלעזר לקח לו מבנות פוטיאל לו לאשה Elazar
lakach lo m'bnot Putiel lo l'isha from the daughters of פוטיאל Putiel
and the גמרא Gemara. says that פוטיאל Putiel is יתרו שפיטם עגלים
לעבודה זרה Yisro shepitam agalim l'avoda zara he fattened cows for עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. So this is a descendant of פוטי, Puti, פוטי
Puti being פוטיאל Putiel meaning his grandfather.
So they were trying, you know, it's like, you know, משה Moshe
was בן עמרם, Ben Amram, you know, everybody's being, their status is
being treated, you know, in a lowly way. Have you seen this
son of פוטי Puti שפיטם אבי אמו shepitam avi imo the father
of his mother, right, because אלעזר, Elazar, you know, married בנות פוטיאל,
bnot Putiel, so, so his grandfather, the father of his mother is
פוטיאל, Putiel, עגלים לעבודה זרה agalim l'avoda zara for עבודה זרה. Avoda
Zara. והרג נשיא שבט מישראל? V'harag nasi shevet mi'Yisrael? This person, he's
got no status, you know, he comes from עבודה זרה Avoda Zara
himself and he is going to kill one of the leaders of
the tribes of ישראל? בא הכתוב ויחסו. Ba hakatuv v'yichaso. So, and
come to defense, comes the פסוק Pasuk and said פנחס בן אלעזר
בן אהרן הכהן. Pinchas ben Elazar ben Aharon HaKohen. We're not going
through his mother here, he is the grandson of אהרן הכהן Aharon
HaKohen and it's coming, God is coming to his defense. אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא למשה, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe, so God said to
משה, Moshe, הקדם לו שלום, Hekdem lo shalom, you know, bring forth
to him peace. שנאמר לכן אמור הנני נותן לו את בריתי שלום.
Shene'emar lachen emor hineni nosein lo es briti shalom. Okay, now again,
I, my take on this very much is that he, sometimes violence
is needed but the answer to that ultimately is that he should
become a man of peace, which actually was the end of פנחס
Pinchas story in יהושע, Yehoshua, he became a diplomat, the warrior becoming
the diplomat. וראויה כפרה זו שתהא מכפרת והולכת לעולם V're'uya kapara zo
she'tehei mechaperes v'holeches l'olam and it says בריתי שלום, Briti shalom, you
know, ברית כהונת עולם bris kehunas olam forever. The atonement that he
brought through acting on my behalf will is should bring atonement for
for eternity. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rav.
Said רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of רב. מאי דכתיב?
Mai d'ichisiv? What's meant by the פסוק? Pasuk?
זרזיר מתנים או תיש ומלך אלקום עמו. Zarzir masnayim o tayish u'melech
al-kum imo. So it's a very confusing פסוק. Pasuk. The normal translation
is like a greyhound or a he-goat and a king who, you
know, nobody can stand against him. It's in the middle of a
פסוקים במשלי psukim b'Mishlei about things that are very, I don't know,
impressive. But still, it's a little, it's a bizarre פסוק. Pasuk. A
he-goat is not so impressive. So what does that mean? So we're
going to read this being referred to our story. Okay, ארבע מאות
ועשרים וארבע בעילות בעל אותו רשע אותו היום. Arba meios v'esrim v'arba
be'ilos ba'al oso rasha oso hayom. So 424 times that wicked person
meaning זמרי Zimri had, you know, sex on that day. So how
are we getting זמרי? Zimri? First of all זרזיר Zarzir sounds a
little like זמרי Zimri
and מתנים Masnayim can mean like, you know, like the hips, so
it's talking about the act of intercourse. The גימטריא Gematria of the
word זרזיר Zarzir is 424. So 424 times did זמרי
Zimri do this act, and the point is going to be that
that sort of weakened him and gave פנחס Pinchas his opening. Okay,
ארבע מאות
ועשרים
וארבע בעילות בעל אותו רשע אותו היום. Arba meios v'esrim v'arba be'ilos
ba'al oso rasha oso hayom. והמתין לו. V'himtin lo. So then the
word מתנים, Masnayim, it's joining והמתין, V'himtin,
waited פנחס, Pinchas, so פנחס Pinchas waited עד שתשש כחו ad she'tashash
kocho until זמרי Zimri was
exhausted, still to be in the act as we've said. והוא
אינו יודע V'hu eino yodeya but פנחס Pinchas didn't realize he didn't
have to wait, he could have just walked in and God would
have protected him. Why? והוא אינו יודע
שמלך אלקום עמו V'hu eino yodeya she'melech al-kum imo that the God
that none can rise against was with him. So פנחס Pinchas should
have, you know, he waited for his opening but God actually was
with him all along. תניא רבי יוסף Tanya Rabi Yosef in a
ברייתא Braisa we taught שישים. Shishim. He had intercourse not 400 and
whatever times but 60 times. עד שנעשה כביצה מוזרת Ad she'na'aseh k'beitza
muzeres until either it means that his actual testicles became like scrambled
eggs or like his semen became like the, like spoiled egg, and
again until he was very weakened.
והיא V'hi and she, כזבי, Kozbi, היתה כערוגה מלאה מים haysa k'aruga
meleia mayim was like a flower bed filled with water. Very graphic
type of an image here, think about the seed and, you know,
seeding a bed and so on. אמר רב
כהנא. Amar Rav Kahana. ומושבה בית סאה U'moshava beis sa'ah her seat
was a בית סאה beis sa'ah a very large area. So, you
know, she, so describing presumably how she was able to have so
much sex, or talking about her thighs, her hips or something of
that nature. תני רבי יוסף קברה שלו. Tani Rabi Yosef kavrah shelo.
אמה אמה *amah amah*, her literally her grave but here means basically,
you know, her vagina was an אמה *amah* wide, so again, just
very graphic descriptions here about how promiscuous or fornicating they were. אמר
רב ששת *Amar Rav Sheshes*, לא כזבי שמה *lo Kozbi shema*, her
name was actually not כזבי *Kozbi* אלא שבילנאי *ella Shvilnai*.
Her name was שבילנאי בת צור שמה *Shvilnai bas Tzur shema*. Now
שבילנאי *Shvilnai*, as we'll see, was a name in some like sayings
that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, popular sayings that refer to a prostitute.
Okay, so she was this like famous prostitute by this
name שבילנאי *Shvilnai*. ולמה נקרא שמה כזבי *Velama nikra shema Kozbi*? So
why was she called כזבי *Kozbi*? שכזבה אביה *Shekozva aviha*, because she
betrayed her father because her father said only do it with משה
*Moshe*. דבר אחר *Davar acher*, כזבי *Kozbi* שאמרה לאביה *she'amra l'aviha* כוס
בי *Kos bi* עם זה *im zeh*. כזבי *Kozbi* another way to
read it is she said her father כוס בי *Kos bi* עם
זה *im zeh*. Slaughter for me through this. Okay, I mean כוס
בי *Kos bi* whatever, meaning you will be able to destroy the
people by my fornicating with them.
Okay, והיינו דאמרי אינשי *vehainu de'amri inshi*, and because that was her
name שבילנאי *Shvilnai*, שבילנאי *Shvilnai*,
that's the popular saying that people have: בין קני לאורבני שבילנאי מאי
בעיא *Bein kani l'urvani Shvilnai mai baya*? Between the reeds and the
willows, what is שבילנאי *Shvilnai* doing? Like, you know, some type of
a popular saying like oh like where there's smoke there's fire, I
wonder what that person is doing there. What would this שבילנאי *Shvilnai*
be doing between the reeds and the willows if not that she's
going there to have sex? Okay, והיינו דאמרי בין קני לאורבני שבילנאי
מאי בעיא *vehainu de'amri bein kani l'urvani Shvilnai mai baya*. בהדי קילפי
דקני שבילנאי מאי בעיא *Behadi kilfei diknei Shvilnai mai baya*? Amongst these
peeled reeds, what is שבילנאי *Shvilnai* doing? Same point. גפתה לאימא *Gafta
l'ima*, and she has fornicated her mother. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
because they called her like, you know, a זונה *zonah*, the daughter
of a זונה *zonah*, so she's brought her mother as well into
her evil doings. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*: חמש שמות
יש לו *Chamesh shemos yesh lo*. That was כזבי *Kozbi's* name. Now
we're to זמרי *Zimri*.
He had five names, יש לו *yesh lo*: זמרי *Zimri*, he was
זמרי *Zimri*, ובן סלוא *u'ven Salu*, so we know that's what the
תורה *Torah* says, זמרי בן סלוא *Zimri ben Salu*. ושאול ובן הכנענית
*veShaul u'ven haCana'anis*, so שאול בן הכנענית *Shaul ben haCana'anis* was one
of the sons of שמעון *Shimon*. So now, although obviously you would
think that the זמרי *Zimri* was not a direct son of שמעון
*Shimon*, especially because it says בן סלוא *ben Salu*, we are associating
him with this שאול בן הכנענית *Shaul ben haCana'anis*. ושלומואל בן צורישדי
*veShelumiel ben Tzurishaddai*, שלומואל בן צורישדי *Shelumiel ben Tzurishaddai* who was the
head of שמעון *Shimon* in the bringing of the offerings in נשא
*Naso* there at the משכן *Mishkan*. Okay, זמרי *Zimri* על שנעשה כביצה
מוזרת *al she'na'aseh k'beitzah muzeres*. זמרי *Zimri* because his testicles or his
semen became like a spoiled egg, so that's זמרי *Zimri* מוזרת *muzeres*.
בן סלוא *Ben Salu* על שהתלי עונות של משפחתו *al she'hisli avonos
shel mishpachto*, because he, again, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says what the word
סלוא *Salu* means, רש"י *Rashi* says it could mean he caused people
to talk about the sins of his family or he caused people
to investigate the sins of his family. שאול *Shaul*, why שאול *Shaul*?
על שהשאיל עצמו לדבר עבירה *al she'hish'il atzmo l'dvar aveirah*, he lent
himself out for a matter of sin. בן הכנענית *Ben haCana'anis* על
שעשה מעשה כנען *al she'asah ma'aseh Canaan*, he did the acts of
כנען *Canaan*, כנען *Canaan* being associated with עריות *arayos* as they are
in the תורה *Torah*. ומה
שמו *U'mah shemo*? What is his name? שלומואל בן צורישדי שמו *Shelumiel
ben Tzurishaddai shemo*. His name is שלומואל בן צורישדי *Shelumiel ben Tzurishaddai*.
It's actually interesting, I actually looked that it seems like the Yiddish
word שלומיאל *shlemiel* is actually learned
from שלומואל *Shelumiel*. You know, they say the difference between a שלומיאל
*shlemiel* and a שלימזל *shlimazel* is that the שלומיאל *shlemiel* spills the
soup on the lap of the שלימזל *shlimazel*. Anyway, interesting to think
that it's associated at all with the fact that the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* associates him with זמרי *Zimri*. Okay, let's go ahead and just
look at the beginning of the next piece, or let's look at
the next piece. כהן ששימש בטומאה *Kohen she'shimmesh b'tumah*. So another, if
a כהן *Kohen*, you know, does the עבודה *avodah* in טומאה *tumah*,
then it says his fellow כהנים *Kohanim* would take him out and
break his head open. But again, it's not so clear how bad
of a sin that is. It's a sin, but how bad of
a sin? So בעי מיניה רב אחא בר הונא מרב ששת *ba'i
minei Rav Acha bar Hunah me'Rav Sheshes*. So רב אחא בר הונא
*Rav Acha bar Hunah* asked רב ששת *Rav Sheshes*: כהן ששימש בטומאה
חייב מיתה chayav mitah? בידי שמים או אין חייב מיתה mitah בידי
שמים *Kohen she'shimmesh b'tumah chayav misah bidei Shamayim o ein chayav misah
bidei Shamayim*? Is this sin deserving of death in the heaven? Because
how do we understand why they're cracking open his head? So אמר
ליה *amar lei*, תניתוה *tanisuha*, look, our משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* says: כהן
ששימש בטומאה אין אחיו הכהנים מביאים אותו לבית דין *Kohen she'shimmesh b'tumah
ein acheiv haKohanim mevin oso l'beis din*, that the, his fellow כהנים
*Kohanim* would not bring him to בית דין *beis din*, אלא פרחי
כהונה מוציאים אותו חוץ לעזרה ופוצעים את מוחו בגיזרין *ella pirchei kehunah
motzin oso chutz la'azarah u'potzin es mocho b'gizarin*. They bring him outside
the עזרה *azarah* and break open his head with logs. ואי סלקא
דעתך מחייב בידי שמים *Ve'ee salka dachach m'chayav bidei Shamayim*, and but
if he really is deserving of death in the heaven, נשבקוה דליקטול
בידי שמים *nishvkei d'liktil bidei Shamayim*, let G-d take care of it,
right? So that's you know the other side.
Of course until now we've sort of
been assuming that if we're being licensed to any of this stuff,
it's because somebody at some point.
בידי שמים. אלא מאי ela mai says the גמרא. Gemara So what
do you want to say? אינו חייב? eino chayav? You think that
he's not חייב בידי שמים? chayav bidei shamayim? Because if he was,
you would say let God take care of it. אינו חייב? eino
chayav? מידי דמי דאמר רחמנא פטר ואנן קטלינן ליה? midei dumi de'amar
rachamana pator ve'anan katlinan leh? Could it be that God gets him
off, exempts him, and we're going to kill him if there's not
some sense that he's חייב מיתה? ולא velo says the גמרא. Gemara
Does that, is that not possible? והתנן, vehatnan, look at all the
cases we've been teaching. מי שלקה ושנה בית דין מכניסין אותו לכיפה,
mi shelakah veshanah beit din machnisin oto lakippah, the guy, we would
cause the guy to die by putting him into the כיפה kippah
just because he did a sin that's deserving of lashings. רחמנא פטריה
ואנן קטלינן ליה? rachamana patrei ve'anan katlinan leh? God exempts him and
we're going to kill him? So yeah, we can sometimes do that
even if legally he's not deserving of it. That's the case of
כיפה. kippah. הגמרא hagimara says no. Now we're sort of doing a
quick חזרה chazarah on everything we just said. האמר רבי ימי אמר
ריש לקיש במלקות שניתנה לכרת עסקינן. ha'amar rabbi immi amar reish lakish
bemalkut shenitnah lekaret askinan. No, we said that we were talking specifically
of lashings for a sin that's חייב כרת. chayav karet. דגברא בר
קטלא הוא, degavra bar katla hu, that the person is deserving of
death. That's exactly how we explained it before. Okay, says the גמרא,
Gemara but how about the other things in our משנה? והגונב את
הקסוה vehagonev et hakasvah stealing כלי שרת, klei sharet, which is okay,
it's מעילה, meilah, but it's not the case. הגמרא hagimara says no.
אמר רב יהודה בכלי שרת עסקינן ורמיזה ולא יבואו לראות כבלע את
הקודש ומתו. amar rav yehudah bikhlei sharet askinan uremiza velo yavo'u lirot
kevala et hakodesh vametu. We based it on the פסוק pasuk of
swallowing up the holy thing and they die. We did connect it.
So this is exactly the question: do we understand these things of
חיוב מיתה chiyuv mitah that they're not deserving of death, or do
we try to find a way to make them all deserving of
death? So far we've been trying to find a way that they
all are deserving of death.
Alright, והמקלל את הקוסם. vehamkallel et hakosem. So now this we didn't
explain before.
Cursing with the קוסם, with the prognosticator. דתני רב יוסף יכה קוצם
את קוסמו. detani rav yosef yakeh kotzam et kosmo. No, he says
the קוצם kotzam should smite the קוסמו, kosmo, meaning God. דמחזי כמברך
את השם. demachzi kemevarekh et hashem. It looks
like blasphemy and therefore again, maybe for social reasons it's too close
or we can infer that you should be deserving of death. So
already we're not necessarily saying deserving of divine death, but there's some
sense that death is appropriate here. Okay.
והבועל ארמית? vehaboel arammit? But how about the case of בועל ארמית?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אקריוה לרב בחלמיה ואקריוה לקרא. akriyuh lerav
bechalmeih ve'akriyuh likra. No, but they read the פסוק pasuk and רב
remembered the teaching. Now רש"י here says, which the גמרא did not
say before, if you look at the six, five lines down in
the wide lines of רש"י, אקריוה לרב בחלמיה יכרת ה' אמר בר
כרת הוא. akriyuh lerav bechalmeih yikhret hashem amar bar karet hu. Before
we had the whole דרשה drasha about you won't have status amongst
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chakhamim, but here at least we're focusing on the
word כרת, karet, right? And that is definitely an assumption
that many ראשונים rishonim make, that there could not be a הלכה
of קנאין פוגעין בו if there was no sense of some sense
of חיוב מיתה chiyuv mitah or חיוב כרת. chiyuv karet. So yeah,
so we did, actually we have been assuming that you need to
find something like that with all these cases in the
משנה. So let's end here. That's what the גמרא is saying, that
it does seem
or it's uncertain: does it make sense דוקא davka that there is
a חיוב מיתה chiyuv mitah or דוקא davka that there isn't? But
the גמרא's approach until now has been trying to find a way
that there's at least some sense of heavenly כרת karet or מיתה
associated with all of these. Okay, we'll end here.